Yohan Chatelain

Montreal, Quebec | (450) 328-6286

yohan.chatelain@gmail.com

Summary

Researcher with 10 publications in international conferences and journals, I wish to devote myself full-time to software engineering. I have acquired experience in software engineering for nearly 7 years through the 5 open-source projects I contributed to or led in C, C++, and Python; and background knowledge in scientific computations and HPC. I loved teaching algorithms and architecture for 3 years to bachelor to master-level students. I am continuously learning new technologies and processes to make better code. What I'm learning now: Rust, Zig, C#, Unity.

Experience

Concordia University | Canada, Quebec, Montreal Postdoctoral Fellowship | 09/2020 - Present

Goal: Studying numerical instabilities in neuroimaging pipelines

- Pytracer author, a trace-based Python tool for visualizing numerical instabilities of Python codes (open-source project / paper)
- o Automatically instruments function with duck-typing and fully written in Python and visualizer in Plotly
- o Supervised an undergraduate internship for optimizing the backend part
- Fuzzy maintainer, an ecosystem for evaluating the effect of numerical errors on computational tools (open-source project / paper)
 - o Provides Python interpreter & scientific stack (libm, BLAS/LAPACK, NumPy, SciPy, Scikit-learn) using stochastic arithmetic
 - o Standalone ready-to-use Docker containers
- o Bug fixer, code reviewer, designer, and new release maker.
- Significantdigit author, Python package for solid statistical analysis of Stochastic Arithmetic (open-source project / paper)

University of Versailles Saint Quentin-en-Yvelines | France, Île-de-France, Versailles Ph.D. student | 10/2016 - 12/2019

Goal: Developing tools for debugging and optimizing floating-point computations in HPC

- Veritracer author, a tool for visualizing numerical instabilities over time (open-source project / paper)
- Automatically instruments floating-point instructions for clang-supported languages (extends Verificarlo project)
- o Implement instrumentation and debug information findings in an LLVM pass (C++) and a post-processing analysis in Python
- o Supervised an undergraduate intern for the development of VeritracerGUI, a Java GUI visualizer backend.
- Development of a Python tool for automatically tuning floating-point precision over time in HPC applications (paper)
- Demonstrate that lowering the precision is viable and achieves 28% to 67% reduction in the communication volume, lowering the energy and runtime cost for large distributed memory applications (up to 1024 cores)
- **Verificarlo maintainer** (open-source <u>project</u> / <u>paper</u>):
 - Development and optimization of C backends for floating-points manipulations with x2 speedup
 - o Development of a C backend to simulate reduced floating-point formats
 - Bug fixer, code reviewer, designer, and new release maker

Intel Corporation | USA, Oregon, Hillsboro Software Engineer Intern | 01/2019 - 07/2019

Goal: Development of optimized mathematic libraries (Numerics US team)

- Contribution to the development of elementary mathematical functions (libm)
- Code modernization (half of the library's function) for ensuring quality standards
- Setting up continuous integration for validation tests suite with internal tools

University of Versailles Saint Quentin-en-Yvelines | France, Île-de-France, Versailles Software Developer Intern | 04/2016 - 09/2016

Goal: Internship for Master's degree validation

- CERE contributor (open-source project / paper)
 - o Development of a new parallel capture in C for shared memory system into the CERE tool
 - o Capture memory pages touched by a thread (with the ptrace) to replay them in a new environment
 - o CERE's experiments have been scaled up (strong scaling)
- Construction of an energetic prediction model in the HPC context
 - Characterization of applications by a piecewise method by using the CERE tool
 - o Microbenchmarking applications to collect hardware performance counters and energy consumption

Exascale Computing Research (CEA, Intel, UVSQ) | France, Île-de-France, Bruyères-le-Châtel Software Developer Intern | 05/2015 - 09/2015

Goal: C codes piecewise specialization based on value profiling

- Implementation of an automatic functions specializer in LLVM (C++)
- Implementation of a value profiling method in Python
- Characterization of speedups gained with specialization

Laboratoire de Recherche en Informatique | France, Île-de-France, Bruyères-le-Châtel Software Developer Intern | 05/2015 - 09/2015

Goal: Implementation of program termination criterion for a generic first-order call-by-value language in ML style in OCaml

Teaching Assistant

University of Versailles Saint Quentin-en-Yvelines | France, Île-de-France, Versailles 2016 - 2019

- Compilers | Bachelor level | 72h
- Advanced Algorithms | Bachelor level | 72h
- Parallel Architectures | Master level | 40h

Supervision

- Master level, Ines Gonzalez Pepe | 09/2021 09/2023
 - o Concordia University | Canada, Quebec, Montreal
 - Subject: "Numerical stability of deep learning in bioinformatics"
 - o Co-supervisor: Tristan GLATARD (50%)
- Undergraduate level, Nigel YONG | 05/2021 06/2021
 - o Concordia University | Canada, Quebec, Montreal
 - Subject: "Optimizing performance of PyTracer"
 - o Co-supervisor: Tristan GLATARD (50%)
- Undergraduate level, Marc VICUNA | 01/2021 05/2021
 - o Concordia University | Canada, Quebec, Montreal
 - o Subject: "Reducing numerical precision preserves classification accuracy in Mondrian Forests" (published paper)
 - o Co-supervisor: Martin KHANNOUZ (33%) | Tristan GLATARD (33%)
- Master level, Damien THENOT | 06/2018 09/2018
 - o University of Versailles Saint Quentin-en-Yvelines | France, Versailles
 - o Subject: "Development of an Jave IDE for Veritracer"
 - o Co-supervisor: Pablo DE OLIVEIRA CASTRO (50%)

Research

Peer-reviewed publications in journals

- Data Augmentation Through Monte Carlo Arithmetic Leads to More Generalizable Classification in Connectomics
 Gregory Kiar, Yohan Chatelain, Ali Salari, Alan C. Evans, Tristan Glatard In Neurons, Behavior, Data Analysis and Theory, 2021.
- Numerical Uncertainty in Analytical Pipelines Lead to Impactful Variability in Brain Networks
 Gregory Kiar, Yohan Chatelain, Pablo de Oliveira Castro, Eric Petit, Ariel Rokem, Gaël Varoquaux, Bratislav Misic, Alan C. Evans, Tristan Glatard. In PLOS ONE (2021).
- Piecewise holistic autotuning of parallel programs with CERE
 Mihail Popov, Chadi Akel, Yohan Chatelain, William Jalby, and Pablo de Oliveira Castro, Concurrency and Computation: Practice and Experience, vol. 29, Aug 2017.

Peer-reviewed publications in conferences

• Reducing numerical precision preserves classification accuracy in Mondrian Forests

 ${\it Marc Vicuna, Martin Khannouz, Gregory Kiar, {\it Yohan Chatelain}, Tristan Glatard.}$

 $6 th Workshop \ on \ Real-time \ Stream \ Analytics, Stream \ Mining, CER/CEP \ \& \ Stream \ Data \ Management \ in \ Big \ Data, 2021.$

· Accurate simulation of operating system updates in neuroimaging using Monte-Carlo arithmetic

Yohan Chatelain, Eric Petit, Pablo de Oliveira Castro, Ghislain Lartigue, & David Defour (2019, August).

In European Conference on Parallel Processing (Euro-Par) (pp. 481-494). Springer, Cham.

· Automatic exploration of reduced floating-point representations in iterative methods

Yohan Chatelain, Eric Petit, Pablo de Oliveira Castro, Ghislain Lartigue, & David Defour (2019, August). In European Conference on Parallel Processing (Euro-Par) (pp. 481-494). Springer, Cham.

• VeriTracer: Context-enriched tracer for floating-point arithmetic analysis

Yohan Chatelain, Pablo de Oliveira Castro, Eric Petit, David Defour, Jordan Bieder, and Marc Torrent. In 2018 IEEE 25th Symposium on Computer Arithmetic (ARITH) (pp. 61-68). IEEE

Unpublished research reports

PyTracer: Automatically profiling numerical instabilities in Python
 Yohan Chatelain, Nigel Yong, Gregory Kiar, Tristan Glatard. arXiv preprint arXiv:2112.11508. (2021)

Communications at international conferences (summary)

- Fuzzy environments for the perturbation, evaluation, and application of numerical uncertainty via MCA in the scientific Python ecosystem Gregory Kiar, Yohan Chatelain, Ali Salari, Eric Petit, Pablo de Oliveira Castro, and Tristan Glatard. SciPy Conference, 2021.
- Towards Abinit on ExaScale supercomputers: the challenge for electronic structure physicists
 Jordan Bieder, Marc Torrent, and Yohan Chatelain. APS Meeting Abstracts. 2018

Communications at international conferences (summary)

- IXPUG 2019: Intel Extreme Performance Users Group, CERN, Geneva, Switzerland
- IXPUG 2018: Intel Extreme Performance Users Group, Intel Corporation, Hillsboro, OR, USA
- ESTN 2018: 8èmes École Thématique de Simulation Numérique, Cargèse, 2018
- RAIM 2017: 9èmes Rencontres «Arithmétique de l'Informatique Mathématique», Lyon, 2017
- ABIDEV 2017: The 8th ABINIT developer's workshop, Frejus, 2017

Education

Université Paris-Saclay | Versailles, Île-de-France Computer sciences | 12/2019

• Ph.D.'s degree | "Tools for debugging and optimizing floating-point computations in HPC"

Université Versailles-Saint-Quentin-en-Yvelines | Versailles, Île-de-France High-Performance Computing | 09/2016

• Master's degree

Université Paris-Sud XI | Orsay, Île-de-France Computer sciences | 06/2014

• Bachelor's degree

Skills

Python, C, C++, Unix, DevOps, Git, Docker, HPC, NumPy, OCaml

Languages

French, English

Links

Linkedin | Scholar | Website